American Philosophical Society Archives 1743-1984 APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
American Philosophical Society Archives
1743-1984
APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
192.25 Linear feet
Founded in 1743 by Benjamin Franklin, the American Philosophical Society was the first learned society in the United States. For over 250 years, the Society has played an important role in American cultural and intellectual life. Until the mid-nineteenth century, the Society fulfilled the role of a national academy of science, national library and museum, and even patent office. Early members of the Society included Thomas Jefferson, David Rittenhouse, Benjamin Rush, Stephen Peter Du Ponceau, George Washington, and many other figures prominent in American history. The Archives of the American Philosophical Society consists of 192.25 linear feet of material, organized into thirteen record groups dating back to 1743. The Society's archives extensively documents not only the organization's historical development but also its role in American history and the history of science and technology.
American Philosophical Society.
Bibliography
Bell, Whitfield J. Patriot-Improvers: Members of the American Philosophical Society, Volume One: 1743-1768. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1997. Call. No. 506.73 Am4me v.226
Bell, Whitfield J. Patriot-Improvers: Members of the American Philosophical Society, Volume Two: 1768. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1999. Call. No. 506.73 Am4me v.227
Carter, Edward Carlos II. "One Grand Pursuit": A Brief History of the American Philosophical Society's First 250 Years, 1743-1993 Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1993. Call. No. 506.73 Am4xc
Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen. An Historical Account of the Origin and Formation of the American Philosophical Society. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1914. Call. No. 506.73 Am43
Smith, Murphy D. Oak from an Acorn: A History of the American Philosophical Society Library, 1770-1803. Wilmington, DE.: Scholarly Resources, Inc., 1976. Call. No. 506.73 Am4xsm
Vaughan, John. "An Account of the American Philosophical Society (1841)." Philadelphia: Friends of the Library, American Philosophical Society, 1972. Call. No. 506.73 Am4x no. 41
Additional information on the history and activities of the Society can be found in its publications: Proceedings, Transactions, and Year Book.
Related Archival Materials note
In addition to the Archives, there are a number of manuscript collections that document the activities and history of the Society. The Library houses the papers of a number of members who were active in the Society, these include the Benjamin Smith Barton Papers (B B284), Albert Francis Blakeslee Papers (B B585), Henry Grier Bryant Papers (Ms. Coll. 38), Walter Bradford Cannon Papers (B C163.1), Hans Thacher Clarke Papers (B C55), Henry Herbert Donaldson Diaries and Papers (B D713; D713m; D713p), George William Featherstonhaugh Papers (B F31), John Fries Frazer Papers (B F865), Ebenezer Hazard Papers (B H338), John Frederick Lewis Papers (B L585), Francois Andre Michaux Papers (B M58.1), Robert Cushman Murphy Papers (B M957), George Ord Letters (B Or2), Joseph Priestley Papers (B P931), William Jacob Robbins (B R538), George Gaylord Simpson Papers (Ms. Coll. 31), and Elihu Thomson Papers (Ms. Coll. 74). Additionally, a few of the Society's officers have deposited their papers in the Library: George Washington Corner, III Papers (Ms. Coll. 11), William Ezra Lingelbach Papers(B L635), and Richard Harrison Shryock Papers (B Sh86). Material relating to the Society's Historical and Literary Committee can be found in the Peter Stephen Du Ponceau Papers (B D92p), as Du Ponceau was a driving force behind the committee's development of Native American linguistic material. The activities of the Society are also documented in the Jane Aitken Papers (B Ai9) - which were origninally part of the Archives (see II "Archives"), the John Fishbourne Mifflin Receipt Book (B M585), Samuel Rush's "Occasional Glimpses at the World, 1824" (B R895.o) - in which he comments on the Society and the Wistar Association, and in the Kane Miscellaneous Collection (B K13).
Three other items that might be of interest include Alexander Graham Bell's address on "Aerial Locomotion" which was delivered before the Society on May 7, 1909 (533.6 B41a); James Bryce's personal reminiscences of Charles Darwin and of the reception of the Origin of Species given before the APS on April 23, 1909 (B D25b); and Randolph Shipley Klein's 1965 master's thesis from Brown University, "The American Philosophical Society and the American Revolution" (506.73 Am4xk).
Other Finding Aids note
The material in the American Philosophical Society Archive is referenced in the majority of subject guides which the Library has produced over the years. These subject guides can be accessed online at Published Guides to APS Collections.The initial guides to the Archive were published in:
Bell, Whitfield J., Jr. and Murphy D. Smith. Guide to the Archives and Manuscript Collections of the American Philosophical Society. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1966. Call No. 016.091 Am3g
Bell, Whitfield J., Jr. Catalog of Manuscripts in the American Philosophical Society Library, including the Archival Shelflist. Westport, CT: Greenwood Pub. Corp., 1970. Call No. 017Am4cm Vol. 1-10
Catlett, J. Stephen, ed. A New Guide to the Collections of the American Philosophical Society. Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1987. Call No. 506.73 Am4me vol. 66s
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
All records originated from the American Philosophical Society.
Scope and Contents note
The Archives of the American Philosophical Society consists of 192.25 linear feet of material, organized into thirteen record groups dating back to 1743. The Society's archives extensively documents not only the organization's historical development, but also its role in American history and the history of science and technology. This amassed documentation can be accredited to many of the Society's diligent secretaries who saved the Society's records and the Society's residence in the same building since 1789.
The record groups are organized around specific categories, such as minutes and bylaws (I), Officers (V), and Financial Records (IX). Within each record group, sub-groups have been created around specific types of documentation. Sub-groups can vary in size from 1 volume to 5 linear feet, with the arrangement alternating between chronological and alphabetical. Early records tend to be better cataloged than later records. To date, the archives documents the activities of the Society through the mid-1980s. Records for the late twentieth century to present still reside with the office of origination.
For the most part, the Archives documents the history of the Society and its many activities. The primary areas of interest are the Society's members and their regular meetings. Minutes and By-Laws (I), for example, is comprised of the records of early meetings and rules of the Society through the nineteenth century. Additional information on the membership can be found in Record Group IV - Members. The bulk of this record group contains records about members from the nineteenth century but does flow into the twentieth century. It includes letters of nomination, letters of acceptance, as well as biographical sketches and lists of attendance at meetings. Record Group X - Meetings - relates primarily to planning and programs for twentieth century meetings. The activities of the Society as an organization can be found in the record groups for Officers (V), Committees (VIII), and Financial Records (IX); the Society's activities as a collecting institution are documented in the materials for Curators (VI), and Library (VII).
The Archives of the Society also provides a useful source for historians of science and technology. During the early years of the Society, papers on innovations in agriculture, technology, and science were presented at the meetings. Communications (III.1) consists of letters and papers on a variety of topics sent to the APS between the 1770s and 1830s. Many of the papers were read at meetings of the Society, some were published in Transactions, and others were submitted for consideration for the premiums offered by the APS. The letters and papers are on topics such as natural history, mechanics, machinery, and engineering, to name a few. Additionally, Record Group II - "Archives" - provides insight into the Society's activities in promoting scientific expeditions and contact with sister institutions. For example, in the correspondence for the 1836 period can be found reports from certain members of the Society to the Secretary of the Navy in preparation for the United States Exploring Expedition for 1838-1842. Material from Committees (VIII.4, 5, 23, 26, 27 & 34) and Miscellaneous (XI 3 & 4) also relate to the history of science and technology.
Record Group I. Minutes and By-Laws 1758-1971 7 ln. ft.
Record Group II. "Archives" 1743-1984 28 ln. ft.
Record Group III. Communications 1748-1837 4 ln. ft.
Record Group IV. Members 1743-1973 15.25 ln. ft.
Record Group V. Officers 1769-1978 43 ln. ft.
Record Group VI. Curators 1769-1978 2.75 ln. ft.
Record Group VII. Library 1798-1977 48.75 ln. ft.
Record Group VIII. Committees 1793-1977 27.25 ln. ft.
Record Group IX. Financial Records 1866-1957 4.75 ln. ft.
Record Group X. Meetings 1901-1980 .75 ln. ft.
Record Group XI. Miscellaneous 1794-1963 6 ln. ft.
Record Group XII. History 1840-1945 .25 ln. ft.
Record Group XIII. Wistar Association 1818-1968 4.5 ln. ft.
Biographical/Historical note
Founded in 1743 by Benjamin Franklin, the American Philosophical Society was the first learned society in the United States. For over 250 years, the Society has played an important role in American cultural and intellectual life. Until the mid-nineteenth century, the Society fulfiled the role of a national academy of science, national library and museum, and even patent office. Early members in the Society included Thomas Jefferson, David Rittenhouse, Benjamin Rush, Stephen Peter Du Ponceau, George Washington, and many other figures prominent in American history.
The American Philosophical Society originated in the mid-eighteenth century, when it was felt a suitable piece of civilization had been carved into the wilderness to allow the pursuit of matters regarding natural philosophy. "Natural philosophy" at that time referred scientific and technological investigations in the broadest sense. The concept of the Society was based on scholarly societies in Europe, such as the Royal Society of London. The membership was comprised of doctors, lawyers, clergymen, artisans, tradesmen, and merchants with an interest in science. By improving methods of agriculture, manufacturing, and transportation the Society hoped to encourage America's economic independence. The Society's place among other international scholarly societies was secured in the 1760s when David Rittenhouse plotted the transit of Venus on a platform behind Independence Hall using one of his telescopes and publishing his findings in the first volume of the Society's Transactions. After a brief lapse during the American Revolution, the Society continued to elect members and became an active participant in the development of the young nation.
During the nineteenth century the Society began to collect important documents of the Colonial and Revolutionary periods under the direction of the Literary and Manuscript Committee. As the Society's membership grew and diversified, so did the Society's interests. Many members in the early 1800s (such as Jefferson, DuPonceau and Benjamin Smith Barton) were interested in the origins and ethnography of Native Americans. The Society's growing Library therefore became a repository for documents on Native American linguistics and ethnography. Based on their vast scientific knowledge, members of the Society were asked to serve as scientific advisors to the Lewis and Clark Expedition, the U.S. Exploring Expedition (or Wilkes Expedition), and the Stephen Long Expedition. The Society also encouraged advances in science and technology through its awarding of the Magellanic Premium. In 1838 the Society increased its publications to include the Proceedings. During the latter half of the century, the Society's primary interests were in the fields of American paleontology, geology, astronomical and meteorological observations, and Indian ethnology.
The twentieth century's advances in transportation and communication brought a new vigor to the Society as members from outside the Philadelphia region played an increasingly active role in the Society's administration. The Society continued to support advancements in "useful knowledge," which grew to include the humanities and social sciences, through its publications and new grant program. During World War II the Society broadcast weekly radio programs on science to Europe. The Society also grew physically. During the second half of the twentieth century Library Hall was constricted to house the growing collection of manuscripts and printed material, and the purchase and renovations of Franklin Hall and Richardson Hall provided a state-of-the-art meeting facility and additional space for staff and collections. Through its annual meetings, grant programs, publications, and Library the Society continues to encourage the discussion and advancement of "useful knowledge."
Naval History Note
Naval historians may find the following items of interest:
Barron, James, 1769-1851.
Barron, James. Concerning the ventilation of ships to prevent the rotting of timbers. 1825 January 7. Manuscript. 5 pages.
Barron, James. Letter to James Mease. 1825 April 11. Sends to the American Philosophical Society a model of Charles D. Brodie's plan for repairing ships under the surface of the water. 1 page.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn. Letter to Francis H. Dercum, President of the American Philosophical Society. 1930 July 15. Letter acknowledging election to the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn. Letter to American Philosophical Society. 1936 May 10. Expresses appreciation for aid rendered for the second Antarctic Expedition. 1 page.
Du Pont, Samuel Francis, 1803-1865.
Du Pont, Samuel Francis. Letter to Benjamin Gerhard. 1861 November 13. Presents an Atlas of the state of South Carolina by Robert Mills to the American Philosophical Society. 5 pages.
Du Pont, Samuel Francis. Letter to J. P. Lesley. 1862 May 8. Letter acknowledging election to the American Philosophical Society. 2 pages.
Galvin, John.
Galvin, John. An improved capstan for ships of war. 1811 February 15. Manuscript. 1 page.
Humphreys, Joshua, 1751-1838.
Humphreys, Joshua. Letter to David Rittenhouse. 1789 January 3. Concerning the regulation of a pendulum. 2 pages.
Humphreys, Joshua. Letter to Benjamin Franklin. 1789 February 16. Concerning scale beams. 2 pages.
American Philosophical Society. Report of Committee upon the plan of an improvement for a windless, presented by Americanus, Navy Yard. 1796 May 12. Report. 1 page.
American Philsophical Society. Report of the committee to whom was referred a model of a temporary rudder...by Captain William Mugford, of Salem. 1805 February 13. Report. 5 pages.
Fothergill, Anthony. Remarks on Mugford's rudder and the proposed notice of it by the American Philosophical Society. 1805 February 15. Manuscript. 3 pages.
Humphreys, Joshua. Letter to John Vaughan. 1814 March 25. Concerning a circular cylinder pump. 3 pages.
American Philosophical Society. Report of committee on Joshua Humphrey's paper on a pump. 1814 April 15. Report. 1 page.
American Philosophical Society. Report of the committee charged with the consideration of the letter of Robert McWilliam on the dry rot. 1820 May 5. Report. 6 pages.
Humphreys, Joshua. Attitude of George Washington toward the construction of a United States Navy. 1837 December 23. Manuscript. 8 pages.
Humphreys, Samuel, 1778-1846.
Humphreys, Samuel. Letter to W. P. C. Barton. 1822 January 17. Short note accompanying description to the "peacing of ships masts." 1 page.
Humphreys, Samuel. Concerning placing masts in ships. 1822 January 18. Manuscript. 2 pages.
American Philosophical Society. Report of the committee to whom was referred the paper submitted by Mr. Samuel Humphreys on a new principle of placing masts in ships. 1822 March 1. Report. 5 pages.
Humphreys, Samuel. Letter to James Mease. 1825 May 4. Cost of repairing a ship. 1 page.
Barton, William P. C. Letter to the American Philosophical Society. 1825 October 14. Letter on nomination for membership of Samuel Humphreys, "Naval Constructor, in the service of the U. S. Navy Department at the Philadelphia Navy Yard." Filed under "Humphreys, Samuel." 1 page.
Humphreys, Samuel. Letter to George Ord. 1826 January 31. Acknowledges his election to membership in the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Humphreys, Samuel. Letter to George Ord. 1842 November 28. Testimonial in favor of Mr. Lenthall. 1 page.
Lenthall, John. Letter to Charles B. Trego, Secretary of the American Philosophical Society. 1853 August 4. Concerning the preparation of an obituary notice for the late Samuel Humphreys. 1 page.
Lenthall, John, 1807-1882.
Lenthall, John. Letter to R. Dunglison. 1843 January 23. Letter acknowledging election to the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Lenthall, John. On the launch of the three deck ship Pennsylvania in 1837. 1843 May 27. Manuscript. 8 pages.
Lenthall, John. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1853 August 4. Concerning obituary for Samuel Humphreys. 1 page.
Longitude.
Byrnes, Daniel. A method proposed which it is apprehended will be an improvement in finding the longitude at sea. 1788 June 19. A method of calculating longitude by lunar observations. 1 item.
Churchman, John. Regarding support for testing theory of magnetism as method of determining longitude. 1789 March 21. Manuscript. 1 item.
Brisbane, James. Letter to Benjamin Franklin. 1789 July 4. How to ascertain the true Longitude of Places East and West of any fixt Meridian. 1 item.
Jourdan, W. Crowley. Concerning ascertaining longitude at sea. 1791 October 6. Concerning ascertaining longitude at sea. 1 item.
Hoskins, Francis. Navigation made easy, or a Mariners complete guide. 1800 May 2. Hoskins presents an idea for a new hourglass-type timepiece and a formula for calculating the longitude without the need for an expensive timepiece. He tested it on a voyage from Philadelphia to Cork, Ireland. The log of this journey is reproduced, and a chart is given as well. Dedicated to Thomas Jefferson, this treatise was submitted to the American Philosophical Society for a Magellanic Premium award in 1800 [see "Minutes," page 299]. It was submitted anonymously, under the name of "Hiram," but a second, almost identical version (dated 1803) was received at the American Philosophical Society with Hoskin's name on it in 1839 [Misc. Ms. Coll.]. 1 volume (15 pages).
Groves, Matthew C. Proposed method of ascertaining longitude. 1802. Manuscript. 1 item.
Anonymous. How to ascertain the longitude. n.d. 1 item.
Laurie, Robert. Some observations concerning longitude. n.d. Some observations concerning longitude. 1 item.
Mahan, A. T. (Alfred Thayer), 1840-1914.
Mahan, A. T. Letter to I. M. Hays. 1897 October 19. Letter acknowledging election to the American Philosophical Society. 2 pages.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1849 December 18. Acknowledging receipt of package. 1 page.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1852 November 12. Letter acknowledging election to the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Secretary of the American Philosophical Society. 1854 October 21. Announcing new asteroid by James Ferguson. 2 pages.
Maury, Matthew Fontaine. Letter to Robley Dunglison. 1860 March 19. Requesting delay of publication of Commodore Wullerstorf's paper. 1 page.
Melville, George W. (George Wallace), 1841-1912.
Melville, George W. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1897 August 30. Cannot attend Nansen meeting, refers to his ship Jeannette. 1 page.
Melville, George W. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1897 October 23. Hoping to attend Nansen meeting. 1 page.
Melville, George W. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1897 October 30. Explaining departure from Nansen meeting, refers to Angelo Heilprin. 1 page.
Melville, George W. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1897 November 4. Sending revised copy of his remarks at Nansen meeting. 1 page.
Heilprin, Angelo. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1898 January 8. Requesting permission for Geographical Society of Philadelphia to reprint George Wallace Melville's talk. 2 pages.
American Philosophical Society. Letter to Angelo Heilprin. 1898 January. Response to Heilprin's letter of January 8, granting permission to reprint George Wallace Melville's talk. 2 pages.
Heilprin, Angelo. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1898 January 19. Thanks for George Wallace Melville's manuscript. 1 page.
Miscellaneous.
A.L.O.T.A. (pseudonym). Letter to David Rittenhouse. 1795 June 19. Includes pen and ink sketches of ships pumps. 1 page.
A.L.O.T.A. (pseudonym). Concerning improvements in ship pumps. 1795 June 19. Manuscript. 5 pages.
Improvement (pseudonym). Description of a ship pump. 1795 June 19. Manuscript. 1 page.
Humphries, James. Description of a model for steering a ship. 1809 March 2. Manuscript. 2 pages.
Voigt, Henry. Concerning steam paddles for boats and mills. 1809 July 21. Includes diagram of paddles. 2 pages.
Patterson, Robert M. Concerning Chapman's steam boat. 1810 July 27. Concerning Chapman's steam boat. 1 page.
Chapman, Isaac A. Letter to the American Philosophical Society. 1820 March 10. Description of a new invented Steam-Boat. With sketch. 2 pages.
Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860.
Paulding, James Kirke. Letter to A[lexander] D[allas] Bache. 1839 April 24. Acknowledges election to membership in the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Paulding, James Kirke. Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau. 1839 October 28. Acknowledges receipt of his diploma of membership in the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
National Institute for the Promotion of Science. Letter to Robley Dunglison, John K. Kane, Franklin Bache and Dallas Bache. 1840 November 6. Forwards constitution of institution to the American Philosophical Society, asks for aid in its establishment and development. 1 page.
Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920.
Peary, Robert E. Letter to Secretary of the American Philosophical Society [Henry Phillips]. 1886 January 18. Asking for article on Greenland. 1 page.
Peary, Robert E. Letter to Secretary of the American Philosophical Society [Henry Phillips]. 1886 February 28. Asking for articles on Arctic subjects which may have appeared in the Society's publications. 1 page.
Heilprin, Angelo. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1897 October. Concerning arrangements for Nansen meeting, refers to Robert Edwin Peary. 4 pages.
Bunce, F. M. Telegram to the American Philosophical Society. 1897 October 20. Gives Robert Edwin Peary's address. 1 page.
Peary, Robert E. Telegram to J. Minis Hayes [sic]. 1897 October 22. Cannot attend the Nansen Meeting. 1 page.
Rodgers, John, 1773-1838.
Rodgers, John. Letter to William Jones, Philadelphia Navy Commander's Office. 1820 January 27. Concerning canvas for sails. 1 page.
United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).
Dickerson, Mahlon. Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau. 1836 August 31. Asks advice as to personnel of scientific corps, and scientific objectives of the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.